<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some reflections on some remarks upon a book, entituled Christ's lambs defended from Satan's rage; written in answer to a malicious book stiled The Quakers unmask'd.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96403</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47683551</idno>
  <idno type="VID">173005</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240892988</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186529</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">47683551</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2661:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some reflections on some remarks upon a book, entituled Christ's lambs defended from Satan's rage; written in answer to a malicious book stiled The Quakers unmask'd.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 8: G. Whitehead.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with considerable loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Pennyman, John, 1628-1706. --  Quakers unmasked.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723. --  Christ's lambs defended against Satan's rage.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Quakers unmasked.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Christ's lambs defended against Satan's rage.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173005:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some Reflections</hi> On <hi>some Remarks</hi> upon a Book, Entituled <hi>Christ's Lambs Defended from Satan's Rage;</hi> Written in Answer to a Malicious Book Stiled, <hi>The Quakers Ʋnmask'd.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>They speak not as Friends, but they imagin deceitful words against the quiet in the Land,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Psal. 35.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Full of Envy, of Murther, of Debate, of Deceit, taking all things in the evil part,</p>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 1.29.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FOrasmuch as <hi>John Pennyman</hi> hath been so Officious as to Promote the said <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> by his particular Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof in his Letters to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Persons, with his desires, <hi>That it might be of some service to them, and that they might be the better by it, especially by that part of it that concerns Oaths and Fighting,</hi> as appears by his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Dated the 23d of the Month called <hi>July,</hi> (as he saith) 1691. I must therefore in these few Reflections on the said Remarks or Libel, apply my self to <hi>J. P.</hi> the person designed to be Vindicated thereby, as the Espouser and owner thereof; his Advocate, the Author, being obscure under a nameless <hi>A. C.</hi> to a nameless <hi>E. S.</hi> Esq; for an empty flourish and pretext, to cover his own mischievous Work of Darkness and Envy, so fully Detected in our late Book Entituled, <hi>Christ's Lambs Defended from Satan's Rage,</hi> that I am satisfied he's never able to hide or clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self on that Account.</p>
            <p>Now then <hi>John Pennyman</hi> we perceive thou art hard put to it for a Refuge to fly to, that thou art fain to accept and promote such a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet for thy defence, as instead of an Answer or Reply, is only some impertinent Remarks, Stuft with Envy, Reviling and Abuse still favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy Dark envious Spirit, which the Lord will farther Rebuke.</p>
            <p>And 1st. <q>That the Publication of thy Book against the People called Quakers, tho now in a time of Liberty, yet looks as if thou envyed our present Liberty by thy pernicious Book, and that it has a tendency in it to bring Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution again upon us, by rendring us obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> Jealousy against us) as much as in thee lies;</q> is both sufficiently proved in our said Book in Answer to thee, and apparent from the tenour of thy <hi>Q. Ʋnmask'd,</hi> and not <hi>that thou art glad of our present Liberty,</hi> as thy obscure Advocate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends. How agrees this with thy Rayling against us, as <hi>double Dealers, false Hearted Temporizers, Lyars, Deceitful Workers, as great Dissemblers, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and Deluders, as have appeared in our Age?</hi> And thus with relation to the Government, to aggravate the matter against us, thou hast put this charging Question, <hi>viz. How dare these Men Appeal to the King and Councils Consciences that they are harmless, and would do them no harm?</hi> How now <hi>John,</hi> do these Passages bespeak that thou art glad of our present Liberty, as thy Advocate saith? And yet thou art the Man that hast pretended to <hi>Abhor that Practice of rendring us obnoxious to the Government.</hi> Thus contradictory thou art in thy Envious attempts, as well as thy Advocate, whose seconding thy Reviling by his slanderously Asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing <hi>Quakerism</hi> with <hi>Teaching to use the basest Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations and Slights that can be found,</hi> &amp;c. will not cover thy dark implacable Envy and Confusion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Instance to prove that the <hi>Quakers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Exhorted Men to Fight, and would Fight them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</hi> Bring thy <hi>Quakers Ʋnmask'd,</hi> and a Quakers Minister, not telling us his Name, saying, <hi>If the Spirit of God in them led them to Fight, I had nothing against it.</hi> I deny the Authority of the first, <hi>i. e.</hi> thy Book being fully confuted, and still Question the last; however we disown the words, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming our Holy Profession, or any of our Ministers, and know no such Record or Book, kept (of Foreign Letters) by the Quakers.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:173005:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> (in contempt) upbraid me for Instancing <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, Prayers, Faith, the Fear of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. For the Defence of the Government and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as beyond Wars and Fighting? Are these no Defence pray? Does not Righteousness Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt a Nation, and Mercy and Truth Establish the King's Throne? If there had been but Ten Righteous persons in <hi>Sodom,</hi> had they signified no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for its Preservation? If we propose a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to a Government by Righteousness, the few Prayers of the Faithful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tho we cannot Fight nor Kill Men, is this all one with <hi>Perjury</hi> in those that can both Swear and Fight? When as we can do neither: Is there no other Defence than Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Fighting? What's become of Christianity then? May not the Heathen say of such Faithless Christians, where is their God? And what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns does he make them to all their pretended Fastings and Prayers, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How cam'st thou <hi>J. P.</hi> to suffer thy notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous false Charge against the Quakers to be reassum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Vindicated by thy Advocate, <hi>as being so deeply concerned and engaged in the late Wars as much as others (or more)?</hi> Whereas thou knowest in thy own Conscience, or at least may easily know, (as it has been plainly told thee) that in the time and heat of those Wars, the People called Quakers were not a People, nor Gathered or Constituted as a People under that Name, nor the Name Quakers heard of between <hi>Anno</hi> 1641. and 1648. And what tho <hi>Worcester</hi> Fight was in the Year 51, 'tis true, still the People called Quakers were not concern'd there. And when they were gathered into Meetings, and publickly become a People, and as such known; there were no Wars in <hi>England,</hi> tho some few there were about <hi>Nottingham,</hi> before that time Convinced of <hi>the Light Within,</hi> but went not under the Name <hi>Quakers</hi> for some time, but <hi>Children of Light,</hi> as they owned themselves; yet then wholly unconcern'd in the late Wars, either at <hi>Worcester</hi> or elsewhere. The Name <hi>Quaker</hi> was first given to a few, by one Justice <hi>Bennett,</hi> a Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor in <hi>Darbyshire.</hi> Where's now the cunning Falshood or Deceit of <hi>G. W</hi>'s Answer in the case, (uncharitably cast upon him?) Thy Advocate al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so very Enviously and Unjustly saith, <hi>That their chief Leaders approved of the greatest things done in the late Wars against the King, and to his Person.</hi> 2. <hi>Of Sir</hi> G. Booth<hi>'s Insurrection in</hi> 1659. <hi>That the Quakers gave Intelligence, calling them Rebels for but endeavouring to bring in the King.</hi> Art not thou <hi>(John)</hi> ashamed of promoting such bitter Envious stuff as this to render the Quakers (so called) offensive? When wilt thou <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> off thy deadly <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Invective Charges against us, as a People that know nothing of them? God in mercy to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Heritage Rebuke the Rage of such bitter Envious dark Spirits. Moreover <hi>John,</hi> an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and general Charge cannot Justly affect us generally more than others (as thy Advocate saith) unless it be justly and Naturally deduced from such matter of Fact or Proposition, as is generally acted, owned or agreed upon by us as a People. For to deduce a general Charge from every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular or private Action, is no just way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, and no better than to Argue, that because <hi>J. P.</hi> once esteemed a Quaker, is an Apostate and turned from them into a dark Spirit of Envy, therefore all the Quakers are such, which is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inconsequent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That thou <hi>(J. P.)</hi> and thy Party and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers have made Disturbances and Interruption many times in our publick Meetings, is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to many, how careful soever thou now pretendest thou hast <hi>always been, never to interrupt us, nor to give us any disturbance,</hi> &amp;c. Recollect thy self better: Thou hast often come in a Spirit of Envy and Opposition with thy Smitings, its well known: Thy matter hangs not well together in this Point; why shouldst thou find thy self in <hi>much danger from the Quakers, or frequently done vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to thee themselves?</hi> p. 2. If thou hadst been always careful never to Interrupt them, nor to give them any Disturbance (as thou sayest) what reason have we to believe that thou wast in so much Danger, or that the Quaker have frequently done Violence to thee, if such a quiet inoffensive man?</p>
            <p n="6">6. We did not dote upon <hi>Charles</hi> II. Nor do we believe that Earthly Kings ought to Rule over Christ's Kingdom or Church, whom he himself is King over; and yet when Earthly Kings are set over us,
<note n="*" place="margin">See p. 11. and 15. <hi>Of Christ's Lambs Defended.</hi>
               </note> we ought to be Innocent towards them, Love and Honour them in their places as Kings of the Earth in outward Government, tho not as Kings or Lords over Christ's Spiritual Kingdom or God's Heritage. I see no Inconsistency, Temporizing or Change of our Principles herein, as is envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously suggested.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Case of the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> is so far from being <hi>far different from that of the Quakers</hi> as stated, that it exactly suits it in their Vindication from the Charge against them, contrary to thy Advocates supposition, wherein he mistakes the Case to suit thy envious turn: The Case of <hi>Samuel</hi> was urged to Vindicate the People called Quakers from <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:173005:2"/>Persons among them did caution Professors against their coveting to set up a Kingly Government, (or an Earthly King over the Church) in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths days; and yet after <hi>Charles</hi> II. was Restored, did Address to him, expressing their Innocence and Respect to Him; upon which the Instance of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> was alledged, <q>When <hi>Israel</hi> cryed to have a King set over them, like other Nations; this thing displeased <hi>Samuel,</hi> or was evil in the Eyes of <hi>Samuel;</hi> and yet for all this, when the Lord had Commanded him to hearken to their Voice, and shew them the manner of their King, <hi>&amp;c. Samuel</hi> in Obedience to the word of the Lord Anoynted <hi>Saul</hi> and Kissed him, and said, is it not because the Lord hath Anoynted thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> see <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5, 6. and 10.1. Dare you say that <hi>Samuel</hi> was a Temporizing Hypocrite herein, or Insincere in this matter?</q> One while he disliked their Eagerness for a King, another while he own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a King when the Lord would have one set over them, (tho it was for a Judgment or Scourge upon them) and yet no Hypocrite in either, which suits our Case as to the Persons unjustly Charged by <hi>J. P.</hi> and his Advocate, therefore his supposition is unjust; supposing <hi>Samuel</hi> their Representative, and the Heir made King (when the Lord shewed it him) it was not contrary to his mind, nor would he have <hi>opposed his Kingship,</hi> nor <hi>vehemently exhort the people from subjecting themselves to his Power,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have patiently suffered under it, as we have done; for when did ever the Quakers, or a <hi>Samuel</hi> for them, so oppose or exhort People as is suggest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Therefore <hi>Samuel,</hi> as Representing them, might both plead Innocence, Love, Honour, or Respect to the King (as they have done) without <hi>Hyppocrisie, Equivocation</hi> or <hi>Deceit;</hi> and you might as well have so accused the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> who after he was Displeas'd with <hi>Israel</hi>'s calling for a King to be set over them, like other Nations; yet when he saw it was God's Pleasure to set a King over them, he not only submitted to God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence therein, but Addressed, Saluted and Own'd him as the Lord's Anoynted, without Deceit or Hypocrisie, according as our Christian Principle hath Taught, and enjoyned us to a peaceable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission (as well as Non-resistance) to the Power and Providence of Almighty God under the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Revolutions of Government ever since we were a People; and we humbly thank God that he has enabled us patiently to suffer when called thereunto, for his Name sake. Nor have we writ bitterly against K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. as we are falsly Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused, (but Faithfully warned him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) but some did Declare against Professors doting on an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly King <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> over Christ's Church <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> and how Earthly or Sensual soever you seem to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he was, or at least, not a Heavenly King, it could not be inconsistent with our Christian Principle, nor insincere in us to Honour him in his Station <hi>as King;</hi> for that we and many others actually did (by submission and rendring to <hi>Caesar</hi> his dues) tho not by feigned Complement.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <q>My Perswasion that the Reason of reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>O. C.</hi> for turning such as feared God out of the Army for their Conscience, was more upon his breach of Promise, than with an intent to have them always continue in it, in order to War and Fight.</q> This Argues not that it was Written with any intent to have had them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the Army, or for any such end as to War and Fight, as 'tis disingenuously Argued against me on the comparative word <hi>More,</hi> being but a manner of speaking in stead of <hi>rather,</hi> my intent being according to the tenour of our Answer to <hi>J. P.</hi> against Fighting, That <hi>O. C.</hi> was reproved for turning honest Men out of the Army upon his breach of Promise, and not with an intent to have them continue in it for War and Fighting, who might have a Fear and Conscience toward God, and yet not be at first so far Convinced or Enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as presently to lay down their Arms and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; therefore it could not be consistent or just in <hi>O. C.</hi> to turn them out for any matter of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but rather to have suffered them to have continued until they had been so far Convinced and Enlightned as to have voluntarily laid down their Arms and Commissions from a Conviction in themselves, as many then did in Conscience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, chusing rather to take up the Cross and to suffer for (and with) Christ, than to Fight for him, or to Enjoy their worldly Profits or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Where did Christ <hi>bid his Disciples to sell their Garments and buy Swords, and consequently to wear Swords?</hi> (As the obscure Remarker Writes, p. 3.) I am perswaded he has put a wrong Remark on Christ's words; who (speaking of Pag or Scrip) saith, <hi>He that hath none, let him sell his Coat and buy a Sword,</hi> Luk. 22.36. And when they told him <hi>here are two Swords; He said unto them it is enough,</hi> ver. 38. Yet they said unto him, <hi>Lord shall we smite with the Sword?</hi> ver. 49. Did Christ encourage them herein to wear material Swords, or to Fight? No sure, they meant Literally, but he Spiritually. He spake <hi>Allegorically</hi> (as some of the Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors declare) and had a Spiritual meaning in send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Disciples into a Spiritual Warfare, <hi>not with Carnal Weapons, but with Spiritual;</hi> for he did not only bid <hi>Peter put up his Sword,</hi> but gives this Reason <hi>For all <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> take the Sword, shall Perish</hi> with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173005:3"/>
               <hi>the Sword,</hi> Mat. 26.52. And expresly Testifieth, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World, for if my Kingdom were of this World, my Servants would surely Fight,</hi> John 18.36. But his Kingdom not being of this World, therefore his Servants or Disciples may not Fight; and what should they were Swords for then? What, to provoke their Persecutors to Kill them? What sayst thou now <hi>John Pennyman?</hi> Art thou of thy Remarkers mind, <hi>That Christ bid his Disciples to sell their Garments and buy Swords to wear them?</hi> Dost thou think it was proper or suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Spiritual Ministry and Warfare to wear Swords and Carnal Weapons, and to Fight with them, when Christ sent them as Lambs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Wolves, among their Persecutors when they Preached the Gospel? If thou art of this Opinion speak out, and tell us plainly, and give us thy Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; if <hi>not,</hi> why didst thou promote, spread or recommend his Pamphlet to any? When Christ said to his Ministers, <hi>Behold I send you forth as Lambs among Wolves;</hi> would it be consistent to add, <hi>But you must wear outward Swords?</hi> Or when he said, <hi>be ye wise as Serpents, but innocent as Doves,</hi> would it be suitable Doctrin to add, <hi>But you must wear Swords?</hi> Or when his Ministers said, <hi>Our Weapons are not Carnal, but Spiritual,</hi> Did they then disobey Christ's Command in not wearing Swords or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Weapons? Answer directly <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>As for avenging our selves in word and Print, Rayling, Reviling,</hi> &amp;c. which he casts upon the Quakers, bringing <hi>G. W.</hi> for an instance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have opposed some envious Apostates in Truth's Vindication, from their Peevish, Malicious Invectives; I do declare Conscientiously that it was not for Revenge that I have dealt plainly with them, but in a Holy Zeal for God's Truth and People, whom they had grievously Defamed, and I know no Characters I have put upon them, but such as I stedfastly believe are very suitable to their ill-Natures and dark envious Spirits, and also warrantable according to the Holy Scriptures: And thou <hi>J. P.</hi> having charged us <hi>with Dissimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Temporizings, Deceivours, not to be trusted in our Applications to the King and Government, and as like the Whore wiping our Mouths by Proclaiming our selves an Innocent and Harmless People:</hi> What worse Characters could we put upon thee? And yet thou hast gone about to wipe thy Mouth, by pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy <hi>Abhorrence of rendring us Obnoxious to the Government,</hi> as appears more at Large in thy <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Ʋnmask'd.</hi> My Reflecting on thy self-Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Deceit, Hypocrisy, and Implacable Envy herein above Thirteen Years ago in Answer to thy said Book in Manuscript, I see no just cause to <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> thee thereupon in these words, <q>God will Smite thee thou Malicious Hypocrite, our Innocency shall outlive thy Envy and causeless Revenge, and rise up in Judgment against thee.</q> I am still of the same Mind, and really believe this Judgment was and is Just and True, and will stand over thy Head, and over thy dark envious Spirit, and thy Associates therein, and that it proceeded from the Spirit of the Living God, shuffle it off as long as thou canst.</p>
            <p n="11">11. I am made concerned again to take notice of <hi>John Pennyman</hi>'s Observation upon a Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the People called Quakers, directed to the present Distracted Nation of <hi>England,</hi> in the Year 659. because his Remarking Advocate has very unjustly charg'd <hi>G. W.</hi> with an <hi>Equivocating Answer in its Vindication,</hi> p. 4. The passage observ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>John Pennyman</hi> is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>We have chosen the Son of God to be our King, and he hath chosen us to be his People; and he might command Thousands and ten Thousands of his Saints at this day to Fight in his own Cause — and give them Victory over all their Enemies, and turn his Hand upon their Persecutors; but yet his Kingdom is not of this World, neither is his Warfare with Carnal Weapons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither hath he chosen us for that end, neither can we yet believe that he will make use of us in that way; but for the present we are given up to bear and suffer all things for his Names sake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Whereupon <hi>John Pennyman</hi> has this Observation in his <hi>Quakers Ʋnmask'd,</hi> viz. <hi>So that they were not then of that mind that the Spirit would never move them to Fight.</hi> And this he brings to contradict their Declaration to the King in 1660. <q>Testifying that the Spirit of Christ, which leads into all Truth, will never move them to Fight and War against any Man with outward Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</q> Which is so far from a Contradiction to the former, that tis rather a Confirmation, and bespeaks they still persevere in their Belief that the Spirit of Christ would never move them to Fight and War against men with Carnal Weapons. Though Quakers did not then believe he would, neither do they now believe he ever will, but the contrary. <q>The aforesaid Declaration Printed in 1659. <hi>J. P.</hi> saith, <hi>was Subscribed by many;</hi> but tells not the Reader that he, even <hi>John Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyman</hi> himself was one of those many who sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed it: as I am sure his Name is to it, with Fourteen more, wherein he hath dealt most Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuously and Deceitfully, thus to Reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Quakers about it, without giving any notice how far himself was concerned in it by <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173005:3"/>mind, if his Malice did not befool him to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look, or not to heed the Subscriptions.</q> And tho his Remarker grants that to that Declaration Mr. <hi>P</hi> —'s (why not <hi>Pennyman</hi>'s) <hi>Name was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the rest Subscribed;</hi> yet to excuse his said Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, <hi>(That the Quakers were not then of that mind, that the Spirit would never move them to Fight.)</hi> His Remarker seconds it with this Remark, <hi>viz. We must needs conclude that this is one of those things that God hath made no Decree to the Contrary; but that he may will it to be done, even by us in the Future, tho he hath not done it at present.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>John Pennyman,</hi> I must apply the matter to thy own Conscience in this Case. <q>Didst not thou in the said Declaration plainly confess our choice of the Son of God to be our King, and his choice of us to be a People, and that his Kingdom is not of this World, and that his Warfare is not with Carnal Weapons? As also, that neither is his Victory by Murthering and Killing Mens Persons, nor hath he chosen us for that end, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> With divers other Passages to the same purpose, <hi>viz.</hi> We do not War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any with Carnal Weapons, neither shall we ever provoke the Nation against us, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than by our Righteous and Holy Walking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Now if when thou Signedst this, thou believedst that the Spirit of Christ might (for all this) move thee (or the rest of the Signers) to Fight contrary to the very Sense and Substance of the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Wast thou not guilty of gross Dissimulation and abominable Hypocasie therein?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>To proclaim to the World that thou and the rest are become Subjects of such a King as will never allow you to Fight?</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>And yet to have this Private or Mental Reserve, that he may move or will thee and them to Fight in the Future, (as thy Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate words it,) I am perswaded the rest of the Signers had no such Deceitful Reserve, if thou wilt now maintain it that thou had'st. Wast not thou very Deceitful to be upon such Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation and Mental Reservation in such a plain Case?</q> Wilt thou stand by thy Advocate's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark in the Case, <hi>That God might will thee to Fight in the future,</hi> when thou proclaimd'st to the World thy innocency and freeness from a Fighting Spirit, as having made choice of the Son of God to be thy King, whose Kingdom is not of this World, and that he has not Chosen thee for any such end as Fighting, Killing, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> Oh! <hi>John,</hi> with what Conscience couldst thou admit of any such Observation or Remark, as that either the Spirit of Christ might (for all this) move thee to Fight <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> to it in the Future? Oh! be ashamed of such perverting Remarks so palpably contrary to thy former Christian Innocent Testimony.</p>
            <p>Suppose that the Government should have Questioned the People called Quakers (as some did) how shall we be secured on your own Principle of your Peaceable Living and Innocency under the Government? May not the Spirit move you to Fight, <hi>&amp;c.? John Pennyman</hi> and the rest who sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed the said Declaration, should have thus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered and Declared, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Though we have chosen the Son of God to be our King, and he us to be his People, and we know his Kingdom is not of this World, neither is his Warfare with Carnal Weapons, nor hath he chosen us for that end, nor can we yet believe that he will make use of us in that way: We do not War against any with Carnal Weapons, neither shall we ever provoke the Nation against us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise than by our Righteous and Holy Walking; (which is our Christian Principle and Perswasion) yet nevertheless we are not of that mind that the Spirit will never move us to Fight; God may will us thereunto in the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though not at present; which if his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth, we must obey, we must Fight and Avenge our selves; we intend to Live very Peaceably and Quietly, unless you provoke us by Persecution or Injury done us; which if you do, then we may be moved to Fight and Avenge our own Cause and Quarrel; and then you'l find us Religious, and not Mercenary Fighters.</q> What a gross Contradiction would this be to our Christian Principle and Profession, as if we could not trust God to Plead or Avenge his own and our Innocent Cause? And what an Affront would such an Answer be to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and what Security would it bespeak thereunto? Might not the Magistrate justly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Reflect, and say, Nay, if you be upon these contradictory and uncertain Terms and Reserves, you are not to be Trusted in your pretences of Innocency and Peaceable Living; we had need to look to our selves, and timely restrain and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press you. Is this all the Security you'll grant us? Had not this been the ready way to bring extream Persecution upon us? Oh <hi>John!</hi> Dost thou think thou hast well Personated the People called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, or justly represented their Case, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Spirit may move them to Fight, God may will it to be done by them in the Future? As if their Principle and Perswasion not to Fight, but to live Peaceably and Inoffensively, were but <hi>Pro tempore,</hi> but for the present time, and not for the Future. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>servation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173005:4"/>in Signing the aforesaid Declaration, 1659? I am satisfied the rest of the Subscribers had no such Mental Reservation or meaning, but the contrary, as some of them have told me, it did never enter into their thoughts to imagin the Spirit of Christ should move them to Fight, so expressly contrary to their declared Innocency to the Government, as being Subjects of such a King, (<hi>viz.</hi> Christ Jesus) as will not admit them to Fight or destroy Mens Lives, which he came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy, but to save. I question not but those of the Subscribers that yet remain (except <hi>J.</hi> P.) would give it under their Hands (if desired) that they intended no such thing or meaning, as he and his Remarker has put upon the said Declaration, for being moved in the Future to Fight. And <hi>John,</hi> thy Remarker his Criticising upon the Particle, <hi>[yet]</hi> and <hi>[for the Present]</hi> as opposed to the time to come, and Importing that <hi>Fighting may be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us in the Future,</hi> p. 5. This will not excuse thee, neither in concealing thy Name, nor in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon others concerned in Subscription with thee; nor yet in Clouding the Simplicity and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of that Declaration aforesaid, by such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Observations and Remarks thereupon by thee and thy Advocate, who both appear very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair and disingenuous; for though the word <hi>[pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent]</hi> be opposed to the time to come, and not very proper in that place of the said Declaration, as was hinted in our Answer, <hi>Christ's Lambs Defended,</hi> p. 37. The words <hi>[Neither can we yet believe that he will make use of us in that way, as to War with Carnal Weapons]</hi> are not necessarily opposed to the time to come, <hi>[neither that he will so make use of us]</hi> being <hi>In futuro,</hi> expressly relative to the time to come, and consequently far enough from Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Fighting may be commanded us for the Future.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And now <hi>John,</hi> thy Advocate charges us with many Falshoods, too many here to repeat, but that of <hi>Exalting our selves, affecting singularity in most things, accustomed in</hi> England <hi>how Innocent so ever;</hi> these are unjustly deduced from our saying <hi>thou,</hi> not <hi>you</hi> to a single Person, calling <hi>no man Master,</hi> condemning the <hi>putting off the Hat to any,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John,</hi> I am perswaded that thou wast once sensible that these proceed not from any affected Singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or self-exaltion among us, but from a humble Submission to the Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ and self-denying Spirit; however, thou art now so far alienated and depraved from that Simplicity and Plainness of Truth, that thou canst Conform to the World in Language and gesture, and then <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> on thy part, even in those things wherein thou once had Testimony among us? Did'st not thou bear Testimony against putting off the Hat and Bowing to Men? But hast thou not made thy self a Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressor in falling into the same Practice again, in building up what thou once destroyest, and that according to <hi>that excellent Principle of Reformation, the Light in every Man?</hi> (as thy Advocate confesseth it to be, p. 5.) by which excellent Principle we are (and thou wert) led, even in those things slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him and thee, wherein we are not (nor may be) conformable to the World. But he would not be understood to <hi>Impute these Immoralities to the Quakers in general, nor to all their Teachers and Leading Men, but to the Foxonian Party that love to Govern,</hi> p. 5. We deny this scornful Distinction of Parties. Here he makes Exception, and yet Vindicates thy <hi>Quakers Ʋnmasked.</hi> What Quakers and Teachers among them dost thou and he own, so as not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute any such Immoralities unto them? Whilst he is Accusing the People called Quakers over and over <hi>in terminis:</hi> What Fallacy and self-contradiction is this, and how Immoral and Unjust is it in him and thee again to upbraid us with a pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Order from</hi> Berbados? Seeing when it first came over it was Disowned by Us and our Friends in general, especially wherein it imports a contrary Distinction or Division between the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in a particular Member, and the same Spirit in the Church, or opposing the particular Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure thereof in my self, to the Spirit of God in Meetings, which we cannot make good sense of; for the same Spirit cannot be Divided; and the Judgment that rises in the Church of God from the Spirit of Truth in any matter, comes from the same Spirit in particular Members, before it be received in the General; and we have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood that the aforesaid pretended Order was then Disowned by some particular Friends, even in <hi>Barbados,</hi> and afterwards revoked by them in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and therefore not justly to be made a Charge against them or us.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Your joyning <hi>W. Muckloe</hi> with <hi>F. Bugg</hi> and others, as <hi>Witnesses against us, and as Grieved and Mournful to see that excellent Principle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, the Light in every Man so grosly perverted and undermined,</hi> &amp;c. I am perswaded <hi>W. Muckloe</hi> did not give you leave to rank him in the List with such as <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> and that you have not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in appeared his Friend, and that he has at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to more Wisdom and Justice than to own or countenance thee J. <hi>P.</hi> or <hi>F. B.</hi> eithe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in your works of Envy and Persecution <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> render us Odious and Obnoxious to the Gov<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:173005:4"/> 14. Another Charge is, <hi>That the Quakers will Fight in a just Cause,</hi> p. 6. His instances for Proof are, <hi>That one Defended himself against three High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-men, having only a Staff in his Hand,</hi> [not a Sword nor Gun then; and upon a sudden sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizal: But did he place this upon the motion of the Spirit of Christ, or Principle of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, or only as a permitted Human Act hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening on such an Immergency? If not on the first, How doth this overthrow the Principle or affect the People with the Charge before? Was this any more than a private and particular act? How then does it affect the Quakers in general?] <hi>And the two Ship-Masters carrying Guns, and Fighting until overpowered by the</hi> Turks <hi>the Enemy,</hi> &amp;c. And what follows? <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Quakers will Fight.</p>
            <p>I deny the consequence, it being unjustly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and 'tis a Fallacious way of Arguing <hi>a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulari ad Ʋniversale,</hi> as to Argue thus, <q>Two Ship-Masters, called Quakers, carried Guns, Fought in their own Defence, <hi>Ergo,</hi> all Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masters Quakers carry Guns and Fight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when the contrary is evident by many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. The Charge against <hi>S. Crisp,</hi> of <hi>forcing the Man to Sign and Seal the Paper,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by <hi>S. C.</hi> what if it be affirmed by <hi>J. P.?</hi> Surely we have more reason to give Credit to <hi>S. C.</hi> than to J. <hi>P.</hi> (in the case) who is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our open Enemy and Persecutor to his Power.</p>
            <p n="16">16. I am not convinced by what J. <hi>P.</hi> and his Remarker saith, <hi>That the Quakers are mistaken about the Nature of an Oath;</hi> let's a little Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin his Definition of an Oath, where he tells us, That <hi>he that Falsifies in the Presence of God call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to Witness, incurs the greatest Punishments of Divine Vengeance, as one that makes God a Partner to a Lye:</hi> And what's the Consequence? <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore calling God to Witness, is as much an Oath as any other form of Words.</hi> And so to Testify the Truth <hi>in the Presence of Him that knowleth all things;</hi> or to say, <hi>God is my Witness. I call God to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord on my Soul. The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ knows I Lye not,</hi> &amp;c. These he calls <hi>Forms of an Oath:</hi> Wherein I think the Remarker is mistaken.</p>
            <p>For 1. No Falsifying whatsoever, though in any Unsworn Testimony can be Excluded either the Sight or Presence of an Omnipresent God; he is really all seeing and present every where, even among false Witnesses, a swift Witness a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If any will Falsify in an unsworn Testimony or Promise; if it be but his bare <hi>yea</hi> or <hi>nay,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Asseveration, and would have it accepted on the Credit of his Religion or Christianity, he does as really make Christ or God a Partner to a Lye, as he that expressly saith, I speak <hi>in the Presence of God,</hi> or <hi>God is Witness,</hi> &amp;c. (Is there no difference between Asseveration and Imprecation?) And as much incurs the Penalty of Divine Vengeance by Falsifying his unsworn Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God is really Witness to every Truth sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Declared, whether we call him to Witness thereunto, or not; so he is Witness against every Lye and False Testimony, though it be unsworn, and it is as Punishable by him; if all <hi>Lyars be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Holy City, and the Lake that burns must be their Punishment,</hi> what greater Punishment is there for false Swearers? Are all Lyes therefore Oaths? No sure, though every false Oath be a Lye, yet every Lye is not an Oath.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Remarker's Description of an Oath, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects on the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> for Swearing and using several Forms of Oaths in his Epistles to the Churches of Christ; as if they were so Incredulous as not to believe his Christian Testimony, without using several Forms of Oaths, or without break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christ's Command; and his Apostle <hi>James</hi> his Exhortation against all Swearing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. We'll rather believe that the Apostles of Christ observed his Doctrin <hi>not to Swear,</hi> than that they contrary thereunto, did Swear several Forms of Oaths; for God being <hi>Witness</hi> to every Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Truth, though unsworn, I cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that simply Declaring either <hi>in the Presence of God,</hi> or that <hi>God is witness to the Truth Declared,</hi> can be either an Oath, or the Form of an Oath, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some Imprecation or Curse, or Invoking of God to Vengeance, conditionally contained or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Form of an Oath; and is there not also some overt Act or Ceremony required in a formal Oath, and done by him that Swears? For farther Answer in this Case, I refer you to a Book Entituled, <hi>The Case of the Quakers Defended, as Evangelical,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno.</hi> 1675.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The Reflections upon us in Conclusion, as mistaken about the Payment or non-Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173005:5"/>of Taxes is mis-stated, as if designed to render us Obnoxious. And if the Remarker will please ingenuously to shew his Face, and Condescend to admit us some Amicable Discourse with him upon his Remarks, we doubt not but to shew him his Mistake in that, and several other things therein, more than are herein taken notice of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By a Servant of Christ,<lb/>
                  <hi>G. WHITEHEAD.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>the 1st<lb/> of the 6th Month,<lb/> 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>